# **RUBIERE** RAMIREZ

**Geospatial Specialist | Spatial Data Engineer** 

rubiere.ramirez@gmail.com

(+501) 636-5355



**Q** 19 Barton Creek Street, Belmopan City, Belize

## SUMMARY

A geospatial specialist and a spatial data engineer with over six years of experience in proprietary geographic information systems (GIS), free and open-source GIS, spatial data programming, spatial database management, remote sensing, earth observation, and spatial data engineering.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### Geographic Information Systems Assistant, Statistical Institute of Belize

September 2022 – Present

**Q** Belmopan, Belize

Administer and maintain Enterprise GIS, spatial databases, services, Web GIS applications and perform earth observation on the built environment.

- Develop, administer and maintain spatial databases on PostgreSQL database with PostGIS extension.
- Develop, administer and maintain web applications on free and opensource software for geospatial (FOSS4G): GeoServer & Mapstore2; and on commercial off-the-self (COTS) software: Portal for ArcGIS & ArcGIS Server.
- Create Sentinel-2 Geomedian of Belize with Google Earth Engine and classify urban areas with machine learning in Python.
- Develop tools to automate tasks and to standardize the extraction, transformation and loading of non-spatial data and spatial data into SIB's spatial data repositories with SQL, R, and Python.

\_\_\_\_\_\_

## Geographic Information Systems Technician,

**Statistical Institute of Belize** 

Create spatial data using front-end geospatial software and produce maps.

- Heads-up digitized building footprints for the entire country of Belize.
- Perform remote sensing techniques to detect changes in urban areas in OGIS.
- Process aerial photos from drone imagery in QGIS and ArcGIS Pro.

\_\_\_\_\_

#### Geographic Information Systems Technician,

**Coastal Zone Management Authority and Institute of Belize** 

May 2017 − June 2017

**Q** Belize City, Belize

Assist CZMAI with data creation and field data collection.

- Heads-up digitized and updated building footprints for Caye Caulker using Google Earth Pro and existing building footprints.
- Assisted with the collection of land use and building information in Caye Caulker using Open Data Kit for android devices.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **B.Sc. in Natural Resource Management**

**University of Belize** 

= 2012 - 2014

Pelmopan, Belize

## **SKILLS**

R | R-Spatial | Python | GeoPython |
SQL | Spatial SQL | QGIS | ArcGIS Pro
| Geographic Data Science | Data
Engineering | Remote Sensing | Earth
Observation | PostgreSQL PostGIS |
FOSS4G GeoServer | Geovisualization
and Geocommunication | Web GIS

#### **ACHIEVEMENTS**

## Enterprise GIS in FOSS4G

Developed and implemented an Enterprise GIS infrastructure with free and open-source software for geospatial: QGIS and PostgreSQL Database with PostGIS extension.

#### Web GIS in FOSS4G

Deployed and maintained Open-Source GeoServer and Mapstore2 with Apache Tomcat on Apache HTTP Server on SIB's GIS Servers.

\_\_\_\_\_

## ✓ GIS Web Application for Census Progress Tracking

Geovisualized census progress coverage by creating a web application using open standards: Mapstore2 web app created using GeoServer, PostgreSQL database with PostGIS extension and ETL process automated with R programming.

-----

## Created {rvr2spatial}

A package in R programming designed to facilitate the ETL process from MariaDB to PostgreSQL PostGIS.

\_\_\_\_\_

#### **Created MariaDB to QGIS**

QGIS Python Plugin that fetches longitude (x) and latitude (y) data from MariaDB and writes it to a shapefile or geopackage and adds it to map canvas.